William E. Fredeman Collection of William Bell Scott, the Scott Family, and Alice Boyd, 1820-1899.: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
William E. Fredeman Collection of William Bell Scott, the Scott Family, and Alice Boyd
1820-1895
1733-1897
C1459
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
4.0 linear feet 6 boxes
Fredeman, William E. (William Evan), 1928-
Manuscripts and corrected page proofs for poetry and prose writings, drawings and engraved illustrations, personal documents, record books of print sales, correspondence, inscribed books, binding dummies, and family papers of William Bell Scott (1811-1890), a Scottish poet, painter, art critic, and engraver, known for his association with the Pre-Raphaelite circle in London, and also personal and family correspondence of Alice Boyd, Scott's long-term companion, from 1859 until his death. The collection consists of materials acquired by the eminent Pre-Raphaelite scholar, William E. Fredeman (1928-1999) from members of the Boyd family, which were once housed at Penkill Castle, the residence of Alice Boyd, where Scott spent much of his later life.
William E. Fredeman was a prominent professor, scholar, and collector of Victorian literature and Pre-Raphaelitism. Born in 1928 in Pine Bluff, Arkansas, Fredeman pursued his BA at Hendrix College. After receiving his PhD in English at the University of Oklahoma in 1956, he joined the faculty at the University of British Columbia in Vancouver, Canada, where he taught until 1991. Best known for his book Pre-Raphaelitism, A Bibliocritical Study (Harvard University Press, 1965), Fredeman also wrote a major two-volume study of Dante Gabriel Rossetti's letters, and contributed to many major projects, including four volumes of the Dictionary of Literary Biography, The Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood Journal, the collected letters of William Bell Scott, and numerous articles and books on Dante Gabriel Rossetti, William Morris, Alfred Tennyson, and the Victorians. From the 1950s through the 1990s, he was also a well-known and avid collector of books, artwork, and manuscripts related to the Pre-Raphaelites and their circle, and his vast collection drew many scholars and researchers in the field. He died in 1999.
The collection includes personal and family papers of William Bell Scott (1811-1890), a Scottish poet, painter, art critic, and occasional engraver, known for his association with the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood in London, founded by Dante Gabriel Rossetti, William Holman Hunt, and John Everett Millais. Also present are personal and family correspondence and an estate document of Scott's life partner and mistress, Alice Boyd (1824-1897). William Bell Scott met Alice Boyd, also a painter, in London in 1859. They began a relationship that lasted for the rest of Scott's life. Beginning in the 1860s, Scott and his wife Letitia lived with Boyd in the summer and fall, while the three resided together at Scott's house in London during the other half of the year. Penkill Castle, the family estate in Ayrshire, Scotland, which Alice Boyd owned, served as an occasional refuge for many artists and writers associated with the Pre-Raphaelite circle, including the Rossetti family, William Morris, and W. J. Linton. Scott completed many books and paintings while in residence, and died at the castle in 1890, leaving many of his papers.
Scott's materials include manuscripts, drafts, and corrected page proofs for poetry and prose writings, drawings and sketches, engraving proofs, correspondence, record books of print sales, inscribed books, binding dummies, and personal documents, such as an address book and passport. Also included are many important official documents, autograph letters and ancillary holograph material regarding the Scott family, including William Bell Scott's brother, the painter David Scott (1806-1849), their father, the engraver Robert Scott (1777-1841), grandfather Robert Scott, and great-grandfather George Scott. Alice Boyd's papers include personal and family correspondence, as well as an estate document regarding her grandfather, William Losh, and an unsigned manuscript chronicling the history of Alice Boyd and the Pre-Raphaelites at Penkill Castle. A small group of related materials, with holograph poems by others and clippings, is also included.
The following standard abbreviations, or their variations, are used to identify materials in this collection: ALS = autograph letter signed, AL = autograph letter, TLS = typed letter signed.
The collection is open for research.
This collection was a part of William E. Fredeman's large collection of books, artwork, and manuscripts related to the Pre-Raphaelites and their circle, which he developed from the 1950s through the 1990s. Fredeman acquired these papers, which were once housed at Penkill Castle, from descendants of the Alice Boyd family.
Purchase, 2013 and 2014.
All materials were retained with the collection, with the exception of a large metal strong box that originally housed the Scott family papers.
Boyd family.; Boyd, Alice, 1824-1897 -- Correspondence.; Scott family.; Scott, David, 1806-1849 -- Correspondence.; Scott, William Bell, 1811-1890.; Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood.; Art, British -- 19th century.; Art and design -- Great Britain -- 19th century.; Painters -- Scotland -- 19th century -- Drawings.; Painting, Scottish -- 19th century.; Poets, Scottish -- 19th century -- Manuscripts.; Pre-Raphaelitism.; Scottish poetry -- 19th century.; Correspondence -- 19th century.; Documents -- 19th century.; Drawings -- 19th century.; Manuscripts -- 19th century.; Poems -- 19th century.; Art history; British literature
- Series 1: William Bell Scott Family Papers, 1830-1890; 1733-1893; 5 boxes
  This series is arranged into five file groups.
  This series includes writings, artwork, personal correspondence, and documents of William Bell Scott, as well as family papers following his paternal family line through four generations. Scott, a close friend and associate of Dante Gabriel Rossetti and other central Pre-Raphaelites, was active in several fields, generating written work as a poet, art critic, and memoirist, and visual work as an engraver, painter, and teacher of the ornamental arts. The variety of materials present in this series reflects the diversity of Scott's artistic practice. These materials include manuscripts, drafts, corrected page proofs, notes, sketches, print proofs of engraved illustrations, print sales records, binding dummies, errata slips, and bound printed volumes for many of William Bell Scott's major works in poetry, prose, and art, as well as for projects to which he contributed writing or illustrations. Also included are assorted early drafts of individual poems and essays, along with various informal notes, stencils, and drawings. His correspondence relates to publishing projects and events.
  Family papers consist of correspondence, estate papers, writings, drawings, and official documents regarding feudal property rights, marriage, and guildry for the Scott family, including William Bell Scott's brother David Scott (1806-1849), a known historical painter; his father, the engraver Robert Scott (1777-1841); his grandfather, also named Robert Scott; and great-grandfather, George Scott. William Bell Scott's descriptions of most of the earlier family documents present in this series can be found in his discussion of the Scott family ancestry in pages 9-17 of Memoir of David Scott, R.S.A.; Containing his Journal in Italy, Notes on Art and Other Papers (Edinburgh, A. & C. Black, 1850).
  - Scott, William Bell, 1830-1893; 5 boxes (1 partial)
    This file group is arranged into three subsequent file groups.
    This file group contains manuscripts, drafts of poems and prose works, corrected page proofs, record books, binding dummies, bound volumes, sketches and engraved illustrations, correspondence, and personal documents of William Bell Scott, pertaining to his activities as a painter, poet, and art critic, as well as to his personal life.
    - Works, 1830-1893; 3 boxes
      Materials are arranged alphabetically by title, with unidentified notes and sketches at the end.
      A significant group of manuscript materials exist relating to Scott's final volume of poetry, A Poet's Harvest Home, first published by Elliot Stock in 1882, and again years later with an "aftermath" of additional poems, published by Elkin Mathews and John Lane in 1893. Of note is a complete bound manuscript, which William Bell Scott copied out by hand, day by day, for several months in 1881 as a gift for Alice Boyd. The manuscript, which contains various corrections, additions, and deletions, also served as a mock-up for the printed volume. Also present are many drafts of individual poems that appeared in A Poet's Harvest Home, including a group of poems William Bell Scott wrote during a flurry of activity in the late 1870s and early 1880s during his time at Penkill Castle.
      Materials related to other published works, including drafts, page proofs, and print proofs of engraved frontispieces for the 1854 and 1875 editions of Poems are also present, along with notes for chapters of his autobiography, binding dummies and title-page mock-ups for books to which he provided engraved illustrations, notes regarding his contributions to encyclopedias, and manuscripts of essays and letters published in various journals. Several bound volumes are additionally included, some containing original prints of Scott's engraved work, as well as a few association copies of his books inscribed to friends. Also of note are several of Scott's sketches for a proposed addition to Penkill Castle in the 1870s and 1880s, following the completion of his murals on the castle's staircase.
      In addition to his individual pursuit of poetry, painting, and engraving, Scott served as the master of the Government School of Design at Newcastle-on-Tyne for over twenty years. Accordingly, these files also contain assorted ornamental drawings and sketches, woodcut illustrations, and decorative stencils related to Scott's study of design and ornamental arts.
      - A Poet's Harvest Home, circa 1878-1893; 7 folders
        - A Poet's Harvest Home, Complete Bound Manuscript, Inscribed to Alice Boyd, 1881 August-September; Bound manuscript 1 item (Box 1-3)
          Inscribed to Alice Boyd of Penkill Castle, in commemoration of the publication of A Poet's Harvest Home on April 15, 1882. William Bell Scott wrote out the poems by hand in August and September of 1881 at Penkill Castle. While some poems contain crossed out lines, annotations, and edits, the layout of this manuscript, including placed proofs of woodcut illustrations, is a very close mock-up of the published version. Bound in green morocco by Roger de Coverley.
        - Early Drafts and Finished Poems Published in A Poet's Harvest Home and Various Journals, circa 1878-1884; 1 folder (Box 4a-6)
          These poems, originally housed together, were produced in 1878-1884, during a period of intense writing at Penkill Castle, following the publication of Poems in 1875. Most were later published in A Poet's Harvest Home. Titles of individual poems include: "1881," "A Dieu," "Continuity of Life," "Despondency," "Destiny," "Ego," "Infancy," "Love and Death," "The Madonna di San Sisto," "Morality," "My Rhyme of Love," "Of Love, III. One Day," "Of Love, IV. Another Day," "Of Poets, IV. Dante and Beatrice," "St. Dominic," "The Twenty Fifth Anniversary," and an untitled poem beginning, "A. B. and C. are well known men..."
        - "Burns: His Cottage and Monument," Drafts of Two Different Versions, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
          The second version of this poem was used in A Poet's Harvest Home.
        - "Iona to Erin", Early Version of "St. Columba," Draft of Poem, undated; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - "The Norns," Draft of Poem, Published as "The Norns Watering Ygghrasill", undated; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - "Ode To The Sickle", Draft of Part IV, undated; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - "Ode To The Sickle", Page Proof, 1893; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Albert Dürer: His Life and Works, Binding Dummy, 1868; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 8)
        [Albrecht Dürer]. Includes three notes by William Bell Scott tipped into the front cover.
      - "The Artist of the Hypnerotomachia Poliphili, 1499," Draft of Essay, 1880 March 27; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Published in the Athenaeum, no. 2735, pages 415-416.
      - Autobiographical Notes of the Life of William Bell Scott, 1879-1892; 3 folders
        - Autobiography Fragment with Four Drawings, circa 1880; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 10)
          Related to Chapter XIX of Scott's Autobiography, "Penkill and Miss Boyd, 1880."
        - Notes Concerning Stephanus Caesenas Peregrini, circa 1879-1880; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 11)
          Related to Chapter XVIII of Scott's Autobiography, "Artistic Inquiries, 1879-1880."
        - Autobiographical Notes of the Life of William Bell Scott (Volume II), Binding Dummy, 1892; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Chorea Sancti Viti, or, Steps in the Journey of Prince Legion: Twelve Designs, 1851; Bound volume 1 item (Box 5)
        Contains engraved illustrations by William Bell Scott.
      - "Christmas," Unfinished Draft of Poem, 1830; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Encyclopaedia Britannica, Vol XII Part 1 (HYD-IYR), Seventh Edition, Binding Dummy, circa 1842-1853; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Gilt seal on cover was designed by William Bell Scott.
      - "If thou wouldst know the worthy man..." Untitled Draft of Elegy for Albert Dürer, circa 1869; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 15)
        [Albrecht Dürer]. Note says, "Printed at Nuremberg by Wolff Drechsel."
      - The Illustrated Family Bible, Title-Page Proof Engraved by William Bell Scott, circa 1876; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - "Jacopo de' Barbarj (Jacob Walsh)", Letter to Editor of Gazette de Beaux Arts, 1876 August 14; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 17)
        Regarding the "Master of the Caduceus".
      - "The King's Quair" at Penkill Castle, 1872-1887; portions of 2 boxes
        "The King's Quair" refers to a group of large historical murals that William Bell Scott painted on the spiral staircase at Penkill Castle over several years, illustrating a poem attributed to King James I of Scotland. In 1887, Scott published Illustrations to the King's Quair of King James I. of Scotland, which featured engravings modeled on his earlier paintings.
        - Drawings for Penkill Castle, 1872 October 13-1885 October 16; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 18)
          Includes Scott's plans for a later "proposed addition" to Penkill Castle in the 1870s-1880s.
        - Mock-up Title Page for The Illustrations to the King's Quair at Penkill Castle, Painted and Etched by William Bell Scott, circa 1887; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 19)
        - Illustrations to the King's Quair of King James I. of Scotland Painted on the Staircase of Penkill Castle, Ayrshire, 1887; Bound volume 1 item (Box 5)
          Printed book with engraved India ink illustrations, etched in 1885 from paintings made in June, 1856 through August, 1868.
      - "Lead, Kindly Light," Brief Essay Regarding the Hymn by John Henry Newman, undated; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - "On Viol and Flute," by Edmund Gosse, Proof Title-Page of Woodcut Illustration Vignette by William Bell Scott, 1873; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - The Ornamentist, or, Artisan's Manual of the Various Branches of Ornamental Art, 1845; Bound volume 1 item (Box 5)
        Includes an introductory essay on ornamental art by William Bell Scott.
      - "Peculiar Portion of Art in Spain" and "Spanish Painting in the Sixteenth Century" Manuscript, circa 1880s; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Consists of a preface and two chapters on Spanish art.
      - Poems (1854, Smith, Elder, & Co.), circa 1854-1875; portions of 2 boxes
        - Proof Engravings for Frontispiece, 1854; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 23)
        - Page Proofs with Edits in Pen, circa 1854-1875; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
          Possibly used to make edits for later version of Poems, published in 1875.
        - "Maryanne" ["Rosabell"], Page Proof, 1854; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Poems (1875, Longmans, Green & Co.), circa 1838-1875; portions of 2 boxes
        - Contents and Illustrations Page Proofs, 1875; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - Page Proofs for First 80 Pages, 1874 December 15; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - "The Dance of Death", Page Proof, 1875; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 5)
        - "Hades; or, The Transit," Retitled "The Music of the Spheres", Page Proof, circa 1838-1875; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - "Lines," Corrected Page Proof, 1842-1875; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 7)
        - "Maryanne," Corrected Page Proof, circa 1854-1875; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 8)
        - "To the Sphinx," Draft Fragments of Some Verses, circa 1854-1875; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 9)
        - "To the Sphinx," Page Proof, 1875; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 10)
        - Errata Slips, 1875; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 11)
          34 copies.
        - Association Copy of Poems, 1875 April 30; Bound volume 1 item (Box 5)
          Inscribed to the author's wife, Letitia Scott.
      - "Popular Tuscan Songs," Draft of Poem, undated; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - "The Portrait of Shakespeare," Draft of Scholarly Essay, undated; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - "The Prodigal", The Fortnightly, New Series, vol. 5 (1869) pages 146-155, Corrected Page Proof, 1 item (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - "Reunited," Draft of Unpublished Poem, 1887 July 12; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Views of Loch Katrine and Adjacent Scenery, 1830 September 1; Bound volume 1 item (Box 5)
        Privately printed author copy of book by William Bell Scott with plates engraved by his father, Robert Scott. Includes William Bell Scott's bookplate.
      - "What time the gold-haired victor sent due west..." Draft of Untitled Poem, undated; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - William Blake: Etchings from his Works, 1877 November-1878; Bound volume 1 item (Box 5)
        Presentation copy inscribed to Alice Boyd. Includes William Bell Scott's illustrations to William Blake's writings. Several of Scott's tracings from sketches by William Blake are also tipped into the volume's rear cover.
      - The Year of the World; a Philosophical Poem on "Redemption from the Fall", 1846-1879 October 29; Bound volumes portion of 1 box (Box 5)
        Two copies of the 1846 volume are present. One is an association copy inscribed to Lucy Madox Brown. The other is a presentation copy inscribed to Lady Wilde with a letter tipped into the front cover, dated October 29, 1879, requesting her corrections.
      - Decorative Stencils for Pouncing, undated; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Engraved Seals and Insignia Printed on Thin Paper, undated; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Ornamental Drawings and Sketches, undated; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 19)
        Drawings include an assortment of 19 cartoon sketches, floral motifs, decorative designs, figures, and borders.
      - Printed Woodcut Illustrations of Tree Branches and a Basket, undated; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 20)
        5 pieces.
      - Unidentified Play Fragment, undated; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Untitled Notes and Lists, 1879 January-1880; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 22)
        Includes a page of notes regarding Jean-Antoine Watteau, symmetry, ornamental art, and painting; a list of names beginning with C-D, for which Scott wrote entries for a new edition of the Edwards Encyclopedia; and a page of notes, reading "fresh flowers, little fishes, row of trees by the riverside" with a list of animals.
    - Correspondence, 1879-1887; 1845-1887; 16 folders
      Letters are arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
      This file group includes personal correspondence of William Bell Scott, primarily letters received, regarding books and publishing, the work of other writers and artists, and invitations to events. A significant portion of the correspondence, dated 1887, consists of letters thanking William Bell Scott for gifted copies of The Illustrations to the King's Quair, an edition of engravings Scott published that year based on his paintings at Penkill Castle.
      Of note is a letter from William Morris regarding a work contract that Scott held with Morris, as well as Morris's impressions of Stonehenge and his decision to take up tapestry work. Also present is a detailed letter from William Bell Scott's brother, David Scott, regarding his views on art. Several postcards from William Bell Scott, along with a watercolor valentine addressed to Alice Boyd, can be located among her personal correspondence.
      - Alexander, Will (Daily Free Press, Aberdeen) to William Bell Scott, 1887 August 4; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Andrew, Catherine N., to William Bell Scott, circa 1887 July 13; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Arthur, James, to William Bell Scott, 1887 July 12; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Blackwoods and Sons, to William Bell Scott, 1887 July 26; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Gibb, E.J.W., to William Bell Scott, 1887 July 12; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Gordon, Mr. (Aberdeen Art and Industrial Museum), to William Bell Scott, 1887 July 19; AL 1 item (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Morris, William, to William Bell Scott, 1879 October 13; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Morse, Juliet M., to William Bell Scott, 1887 July 13; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Reid, Florence, to William Bell Scott, circa 1887 July 24; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Scott, David, to William Bell Scott, 1845 March 2; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 10)
        This lengthy letter contains David Scott's answers to many questions on art and philosophy that William Bell Scott had posed to him over the years. William Bell Scott published his brother's memoirs in 1850, likely using many of these insights therein.
      - Wallis, Henry, from William Bell Scott, 1887 October 23; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Way, William Cosens, to William Bell Scott, 1884 July 26; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Wilde, Lady [Jane] (1821-1896), from William Bell Scott, 1879 October 29; Photocopy of ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 13)
        The original letter can be found tipped into the cover of the presentation copy of The Year of the World inscribed to Lady Wilde, located in Box 5.
      - Winthrop, Annie, to William Bell Scott, circa 1887 July 25; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Wordie, John, to William Bell Scott, 1887 August 4; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Unidentified Person, to William Bell Scott, undated; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 16)
        Signed "U.F.U."
    - Personal Documents, circa 1854-1890; 2 boxes (1 partial)
      Items within this file group are arranged alphabetically by format.
      This file group includes personal documents and effects belonging to William Bell Scott, which remained at Penkill Castle after his death. Included are Scott's address book listing the names and addresses of his friends and fellow artists and writers, as well as notes on his models and travel arrangements, a passport bearing many stamps from his frequent trips to Italy and France in the 1850s and early 1860s, calling cards for Scott and Alice Boyd, and an envelope of Dante Gabriel Rossetti's monogram stamps that Scott kept with his effects. Also present is a small document box bearing Scott's monogram, in which he stored many of his most personal documents. Of note are two record books documenting prints sold by Scott, including prices, type, and location information for artwork sold between 1870 and 1884.